White House Tapes: Conversation 947-004, July 10, 1973
National Archives and Records Administration
Society of American Archivists
White House Tapes: Conversation 947-004
July 10, 1973
Nixon, Richard M. (President); Shultz, George P.; Ford, Gerald R.; Scott, Hugh; Timmons, William E.; Ziegler, Ronald L.
597542 White House Tapes 17409633 Oval Office Sound Recordings 7450149 Audiotape 947
Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum
947-004
On July 10, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, George P. Shultz, Gerald R. Ford, Hugh Scott, William E. Timmons, and Ronald L. Ziegler met in the Oval Office of the White House from 10:24 am to 11:02 am. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 947-004 of the White House Tapes. Topics of conversation included the national economy; the Nixon Administration's economic policies and actions, specifically Phase IV of the Economic Stabilization Program under the Economic Stabilization Act of 1970; and balanced budget efforts for the federal budget.
This Oval Office recording is part of the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes, a secret taping program authorized by President Richard Nixon and active from 1971 to 1973.
July 10, 1973
July 10, 1973
certain
10:24 am
11:02 am
certain
Recording Location and Taping System History
Beginning in 1971, President Richard Nixon authorized the installation of a secret taping system in selected portions of the White House, Cabinet Room, Oval Office, Old Executive Office Building, and Camp David. Collectively, these recordings constitute the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes.
In February 1971, the United State Secret Service installed listening devices in the White House. They placed seven microphones in the Oval Office: five in the President's desk and one on each side of the fireplace. The Secret Service technicians wired these devices to central mixers that were then connected to recorders in an old locker room in the White House basement. These recordings became known as the Oval Office recordings.
This system was a secret taping system maintained by the Secret Service. Only President Nixon, H. R. Haldeman, and a few of the President's close personal assistants knew the system existed. One of its key features was that the recording equipment in the Oval Office, the EOB office, at Camp David, and on the telephones was sound-activated, operating without a conscious decision by the President to record a specific conversation. The taping system was tied to the Presidential Locator System, which was also operated by the Secret Service, and was designed to continue recording for fifteen to thirty seconds after the President left the room.
On July 16, 1973, Special Assistant to the President Alexander Butterfield revealed the existence of the White House taping system during his testimony before the Senate Watergate Committee. Following this public revelation, White House Chief of Staff Alexander Haig ordered the removal of the entire presidential taping system.
Collection Overview
Conversation Summary
On July 10, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, George P. Shultz, Gerald R. Ford, Hugh Scott, William E. Timmons, and Ronald L. Ziegler met in the Oval Office of the White House from 10:24 am to 11:02 am. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 947-004 of the White House Tapes.
Topics of conversation included the national economy; the Nixon Administration's economic policies and actions, specifically Phase IV of the Economic Stabilization Program under the Economic Stabilization Act of 1970; and balanced budget efforts for the federal budget.
Audio Quality
The audio quality of the Nixon White House Tapes is generally poor. While some locations generated better quality recordings than others, inferior recording equipment, cheap tape stock, improper microphone placement, taping system malfunctions, volume fluctuation, background noise, and electrical interference contributed to the poor quality of the recordings. Other noises greatly affect the audibility of conversations, including such small happenings as the signing of documents or the clinking of coffee cups.
As a result of the microphone coverage, Oval Office conversations have clear audio relative to other Nixon White House Tapes. Even still, extraneous room noises and background sounds are evident and can obscure portions of conversations. The microphones in the desk picked up the sound of anyone writing on the desk or the setting down a coffee cup or a glass. Furthermore, the desk microphones captured the sound of President Nixon's chair banging into the desk, the President's feet banging on the desk as he put his feet up, and the sound of the President's knees knocking against the kneewell of his desk. The microphone installed near the telephone captured the ringing of the telephone, which sometimes blocked out small portions of conversation. On occasion, the helicopter rotor blades from Marine One completely obliterated conversation taking place in the Oval Office. The recording system also captured the sirens of ambulances, fire engines, and police vehicles as they blared in through open windows. On occasion, the opening and closing of interior and exterior doors briefly interfered with conversations.
Nature of the Recording
The White House Tapes comprise secretly recorded human conversation. Most participants were unaware that their meetings and telephone calls were being recorded. The taping system captured often unstructured and free-flowing discussions between close personal associates intimately familiar with the topic. As a result, users may find the recorded conversations difficult to follow.
Collection Arrangement
About the Subject Log
To assist listeners in understanding the conversation and finding segments pertinent to their own interests, a team of archivists has created a Subject Log, which outlines major topics, names, and organizations in sequential order.
Logs include action statements, which indicate when someone entered or exited a room. Action statements are underlined.
If a conversation recorded in one of the offices also captures a telephone conversation, a cross-reference to the corresponding telephone recording is provided.
If a telephone recording also captures a conversation taking place in one of the offices, a cross-reference to the corresponding room conversation is provided.
Logs indicate which portions, if any, were reviewed under the 2007 Deed of Gift.
In some cases, the Watergate Special Prosecution Force or court-ordered mandates resulted in a transcript of the entire conversation or portions of conversation. For these portions, archivists have provided a citation to the related transcript.
Audio Format
This conversation was recorded to audiotape on a system maintained by the United States Secret Service. The National Archives transferred the original audiotape to Digital Audio Tape (DAT), which, in turn, was later converted to digital audio files.
The audio recording of this conversation has been digitized and made available to the public.
The White House Tapes are currently undergoing preservation remastering, from which digital derivatives will be made and released to the public as appopriate.
Determination Categories
These processing categories are governed by the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA); and the 2007 Deed of Gift. These categories are based upon the constitutional and statutory duties of the President of the United States, as well as the Watergate investigation.
Location of Recording
Oval Office, White House, Washington, D.C.
Related Topics
United States. President (1969-1974: Nixon); Audiotapes; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Presidents -- United States
Topics of Conversation
People
Ford, Gerald R.; Nixon, Richard M. (President); Scott, Hugh; Shultz, George P.; Timmons, William E.; Ziegler, Ronald L.
Places and Governments
United States
Organizations
Economic Stabilization Program (U.S.)
Topics
Economic conditions; Economic policy; Economic stabilization
Digitized Audio
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as an MP3 file.
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as a Broadcast WAVE Format (BWF) file.
Conversation Subject Log
- The President met with George P. Shultz, Gerald R. Ford, Hugh Scott, William E. Timmons, and Ronald L. Ziegler. This recording began while the conversation was in progress.
  - National economy
    - President's statement on Phase IV of the Economic Stabilization Program
      - Timing
      - Rationale
      - Implementation
        - Timing
      - Consultations
        - Congress
        - Labor
        - Reports
      - President's decision
        - 60-day price freeze
      - Character
        - Compared to Phase III
        - Selectivity
      - Consultation
        - Congress
          - Recess
      - Decision
      - Mandatory controls
        - President's statement
        - Composition
        - Strength
        - Extent, area
      - Consultation with Congress
        - Food prices
        - Supplies
        - Meat
        - Future inflation
        - Balanced budget
          - 1974
          - Ceiling
          - Revenue bills
            - President's veto
            - Congressional override
          - Domestic and defense spending
            - John G. Tower
          - Defense spending
            - Ceiling
            - Fiscal year 1973
              - Target
            - Congress reaction
            - Fiscal year 1974
              - Ceiling
              - Balanced budget
              - Tax increases
              - Senate estimate
                - Caucus
                - Committee
            - Appropriations
              - House of Representatives
              - Vetoes
                - Health, Education, and Welfare [HEW]
                - Farm bill
                - Earl L. Butz
                - Escalator
                - Contradiction
                - Food stamps
                - Increases
                - Uses
                - President's dislike
    - President's program
      - Principles
      - Supplies
        - Scott's assessment
          - Effect in 1974
          - Rationing
        - Meat
          - Chicken and pork
          - Beef
            - Thieves
        - Farm labor
          - Braceros
          - Lettuce, asparagus
          - Southern California
          - African Americans
          - Japanese Americans
          - Mexican Americans
        - Victory gardens
          - Agriculture Department
      - Productivity commission
        - Charles H. Percy
          - Schultz's note
        - Legislation
        - Legal requirement
        - Volunteerism
        - Steel, Construction
        - Continued authorization
      - Inflation, unemployment
        - Rates
        - Effects
        - Priority
        - Congress roll
          - Budget
          - Legislation
        - Business, labor, farmer roles
      - Freeze
        - Effects
      - Possible congressional pay raise
        - Scott's conversation with Ford
          - Everett M. Dickson [?]
          - Minority view
          - Capital extension
        - Carl B. Albert's comments to Thomas P. ("Tip") O'Neill and Leslie C. Arends
        - Vice President, Speaker of the House, President, Congressional Party leaders
        - 1968 law
        - Political considerations
          - 1974 elections
        - O'Neill
        - Albert
          - US Senate vote
          - Rules committee
        - Hiram L. Fong and Gale W. McGee bill
          - Commission
      - Flexible investment tax credit
        - Forced savings
        - Arthur F. Burns
        - Percy, Wilbur D. Mills
        - Endorsements from Wall Street Journal, Christian Science Monitor, New York Times
        - Congressional action
- Ford, Scott, Timmons, and Ziegler left at 10:45 am.
  - National economy
    - US dollar
    - Effect of export controls
      - Devaluation
    - Meeting of European central bankers in Bonn, West Germany
    - Intervention in exchange markets
      - Support
      - Foreign exchange market reaction
      - US commitments
      - Views of Burns and Paul A. Volcker
    - President's programs
      - Export controls
        - Corn
          - Crop reports
      - Phase IV
        - Decision
      - Credibility
      - Effect on exchange markets
      - Europeans' view
        - Experience with price and wage freezes
        - Fiscal and monetary policy
      - Fiscal and monetary policy
        - Budget statement
        - Memorandum
        - Meeting
          - Bryce N. Harlow
            - Forthcoming meeting with President
            - Interpretation of fiscal matters
        - Shultz's recommendations
        - Forthcoming statements by Ford and Scott
        - Timing of decision
        - President's statement
          - Joint session of Congress
      - Intervention in exchange markets
      - President's programs
        - Statement
          - Congress
            - Partisanship
        - Harlow's view
        - Phase IV
        - John Dunlop's view
        - Federal budget
          - Fiscal discipline
          - Possible spending cuts
          - Possible tax increase
            - Joint Committee
            - Spending ceiling
          - Size of deficit
            - Possible vetoes
              - HEW
            - National defense
              - Cuts
                - Congressional action
                - Rates
            - Memorandum
      - Intervention in exchange markets
        - Burns
        - Federal Reserve
        - President's decision
      - Federal budget
        - Percy's statement in previous meeting
          - Burns's viewpoint
        - Debt ceiling
          - House Ways and Means Committee
          - Barber B. Conable, Jr.
          - Mills
        - Tax increases
          - Burns's viewpoint
        - Gasoline tax
          - Possible cut in income tax
            - Delay
            - Spending
        - Surcharge on income and corporate taxes
          - 1968
        - Variable investment tax credit
          - Revenue
        - Possible congressional tax legislation
          - Closure of loopholes
          - Wall Street reaction
        - Gasoline tax
          - Conservation
          - Tax reform discussions
            - Compared to income tax
          - Cost of living increase
            - Regressive tax
            - Income tax credit
        - Republican enthusiasm
        - Ways and Means Committee action
        - Budget surplus
        - Laird, Harlow
      - President's program
        - Statement
        - Joint Session of Congress
        - Substance
- Shultz left at 11:02 am.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This conversation has no restrictions and is fully open to the public.
Access is governed by the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA); Nixon Public Access Regulations 36 CFR 1275 of the NARA Code of Federal Regulations, including the 1996 Tapes Settlement Agreement (Appendix A); and protocols related to classified national security information, including Executive Order 13526.
For more information, please contact the Tapes Team at the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum: nixon@nara.gov or (301) 837-3290.
Acquisitions Information
Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974
The Nixon-era White House Tapes are subject to the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA). PRMPA, which applies only to the Nixon Presidential Materials, stipulates that those materials relevant to the understanding of Abuse of Governmental Power and Watergate are to be processed and released to the public prior to the release of all other materials. Materials related to the Abuse of Governmental Power and the constitutional and statutory duties of the President and his White House staff are retained by the National Archives. PRMPA mandated the promulgation of access restrictions for the processing of the Nixon Tapes.
The resulting Nixon Public Acccess Regulations 36 CFR 1275 state that the National Archives must segregate and return to the estate of former President Nixon those materials identified as purely "personal-private" or "personal-political," and unrelated to the President's constitutional and statutory duties. This conversation has been processed under these regulations.
2007 Deed of Gift
However, in 2007, the estate of Richard Nixon negotiated a Deed of Gift with the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum. By this agreement, materials deemed "personal-political" have been deeded back to the National Archives for release to the public. Materials originally deemed "person-private" have been deeded back to the National Archives, with the exception of materials concerning the medical history or non-Watergate-related personal finances of Richard Nixon or the non-public activities of the First Family.
This conversation has been re-reviewed under the provisions of the 2007 Deed of Gift between the estate of Richard Nixon and the National Archives. Changes in access have been noted.
Description, encoding, and public access to the White House Tapes subject logs are supported by a partnership between the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum and the Office of Innovation at the National Archives and Records Administration.
Digitization of the White House Tapes and related activities by the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum are supported by the Preservation Programs Division and the Office of Innovation at the National Archives and Records Administration.
Encoded by Amanda T. Ross, January 15, 2016
Edited by Amanda T. Ross, July 2016